<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true declaration concerning the surrender of Bridgewater written by Coll. Edmond Wyndham : to vindicate him from some false and scandalous reports ...</title>
            <author>Wyndham, Edmond.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34101</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13764665</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13764665</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101713</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101713)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1055:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true declaration concerning the surrender of Bridgewater written by Coll. Edmond Wyndham : to vindicate him from some false and scandalous reports ...</title>
                  <author>Wyndham, Edmond.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101713:1"/>
            <p>A True DECLARATION concerning the ſurrender of BRIDGEVVATER.</p>
            <p>VVritten by Coll. EDMOND VVYNDHAM,</p>
            <p>To vindicate him from ſome falſe and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous reports, raiſed by ſome mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:101713:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101713:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an old ſaying, that it is better to be fortunate then wiſe; I may truly adde in what concernes my ſelfe, with relation to the ſcandalls that are throwne upon me, by the practiſe and mallice of ſuch as endevour to traduce my reputation, that it is better to be ſucceſſefull then honeſt. For the one I am confident would have preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me in a fayre opinion and good eſteeme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all men, wheras the other only continues my credit with thoſe that perſonally know me; and by that knowledge are confirmed in their beleefe of my integrity. I did beleeve that my owne innocency had beene a ſufficient ſhield to guard and defend me from the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reports of my enemies, whoſe rumors being falſe, and wanting the baſis of truth, for their foundation, I imagined they would quickly vaniſh and not prejudice my honour; and therefore I contemned and deſpiſed them and their authors. But finding that theſe untrue ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, although they have no colour of truth, by the ſlie and ſubtile inſinuations of my adverſaries, have gained credit with ſome noble perſonages, whoſe ſatisfaction I deſire: and alſo to vindicate my owne reputation, leſt ſilence ſhould conclude my guilt, I have thought fit and am perſwaded by ſome friends, to juſtifie my ſelfe by this true relation, under my owne hand of my behaviour in my command, which I ſhall maintaine with my life, againſt the ſcandalls and aſperſions of all my adverſaries. And I am the rather induced hereunto, becauſe I have now nothing left me, but my reputation, which in the cauſe I have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken cannot truely be blemiſht. And I ſhall I hope by this Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, (although it be an inconvenience, that truth and honeſty muſt be enforced thereunto, whilſt treachery and falſhood walke openly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out checke or controule) ſatisfie all ingenuous and honorably diſpoſed perſons, that it remaines yet ſpotleſſe. For if I am guiltie of any crime, it cannot be leſſe in betraying the truſt repoſed in me then trechery or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101713:3"/>cowardice, or both, and I muſt juſtifie my ſelfe that I am guilty of neither, but if my accuſers had beene more moderate, and had laid to my charge, folly, raſhneſſe, or indiſcretion, I ſhould have beene ſo modeſt as not to have juſtified all my actions: For I ſhould have confeſs'd that ſouldiery was not originally my profeſſion, and that I might be guilty of ſome ſuch imperfections. But the ſcandall of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is of too venemous a nature to be digeſted; for it not onely deſtroys me, but diſhonours my Familie, and ſtaines my Poſteritie. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to wipe away this blemiſh, I haue put pen to paper, and doe heere deliver the impartiall truth of my proceedings, which if any man can contradict, I ſhall deſire no favour in their forbearance. I know well that guilt is of the nature of filthy odours, who by ſtirring become more unſavoury, but vertue and integrity is of a contrary quality, which by ſifting and ſearching becomes the more pure and refined; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in confidence of my owne innocency, I doe publiſh this Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein I doe challenge all my enemies to detect me, if I be guilty of any miſcariage of ſo high a nature as is laid to my charge, hoping hereby to make it appeare that I am free and cleere from thoſe blacke calumnies and ſlanders, which malice, envy, and detraction have throwne upon me.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe that according to the dictates of my owne conſcience and reaſon, and according unto the obligation I ſtood engaged unto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, as well by my common allegiance, as by my more perticular du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of perſonall ſervice, in the beginning of theſe unhappy differences and diviſions of the Kingdome, I engaged my ſelfe on his Majeſties party, wherein I have conſtantly perſever'd either in acting or ſuffering untill this day; concurring with thoſe of the contrary party, onely in hating deteſtable newtrality. According to my beſt ability I did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently execute all ſuch Commiſſions as I did receive from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and in the place of Governour of Bridgewater, did uſe my utmoſt endeavour to preſerve that Towne, and to retaine the people in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his Majeſtie. But I, like other of his Majeſties Commanders, wanted the ſinews of Warre, and was enjoyned a hard taske, to make bricke without ſtrawe, to fortifie a Towne, victuall it, leavy men, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101713:3"/>arms and ammunition, with all things neceſſary for the defence thereof, without money to effect it. I acknowledge I had an aſſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of contribution, after long ſolicitation to a fit proportion to doe the worke; but this was preſently anticipated by particular orders of my ſuperiour Officers, and by free quarterings, ſo that very little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney could be gathered by my Collectors, but all or the moſt part was diverted into other chanells, eſpecially of late for the maintenance of the new erected Garriſons of Lamport and Burrowe. And the Lord Gorings horſe by their free quarter and trenchar money ſo impoveriſht the Country, that for the ſpace of ſix monthes before the ſurrender of Bridgewater, I am aſſured I did not receive three hundred pounds, I beleeve not two hundred pounds towards the payment of my Gariſon, and the furniſhing of it with all things neceſſary for the defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I did often complaine of my wants, both to the Princes Councell, and to the ſuperiour Officers of his Majeſties armies, ſo that my defects were apparently knowne unto them, yet could have no redreſſe, untill the Country was poſſeſt by the Parliaments forces, and then it was too late to make uſe of thoſe unprofitable graunts, which were as diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultly obtained, as if they had beene for my proper benefit, and not for his Majeſties uſe. And yet during thoſe laſt 6 months, I had my men, ammunition, and victualls, which I had procured by my own expence and credit, commanded out of my Garriſon, to ſupply the armie before Taunton, whilſt it was under Sir R. Grenvil, and afterward under my Lord Goring, which was promiſed to be reſtored, but the performance came too ſlow. That the Towne lay conveniently to be fortified is moſt apparent, and that with expence it might have beene made very ſtrong is moſt certain, but that it was ſo by the then made fortifications the contrary is manifeſt through want of meanes to effect the ſame. For almoſt halfe the Towne which is called Eaſtover, when Sir Thomas Fairefax came before it, had onely a dike caſt without any faſhioning or turfing of the workes, or forming of the flankers, ſo that although the Graffe were a good defence in the outſide, yet the inſide could hardly be made uſe of as a convenient breſtworke.</p>
            <p>But that which was moſt to my prejudice, was, that ſuch ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101713:4"/>as I had raiſed in that County by my intereſt, were alwayes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded away out of my Garriſon; ſo that when the enemy came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the town, I had not above two hundred and fifty of my old ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers left in the town, beſides towneſmen, the reſt were made up by Pembrokeſhire men, taken by my Lord Gerrard in that County, and ſent over to recruit Prince Ruperts Regiment after the battell of Naze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and I had likewiſe ſome of Sir John Stawels regiment, and ſome few ſouldiers belonging unto Briſtoll Garriſon, which were newly come from Lamport. Theſe came into the town not above three dayes before the enemie came before it, and the Pembroke-ſhire men were ſuch, for the moſt part, as had formerly ſerved the Parliament. They were in number about five hundred, and had the guard of that part of the towne, called Eaſtover, divided from the reſt of the town by the river, and were appointed to defend two third parts of that line; the other third part being to be maintained by thoſe of Sir John Stawells regiment, and thoſe Briſtoll ſouldiers which came from Lamport; ſo that there was in that part of the town about ſeven hundred ſouldiers, I having put more men into it then into the other part of the town, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the line was not perfected, and becauſe Sir Thomas Fairfax with moſt of his horſe and foot lay on that ſide of the town; Major Generall Maſſey keeping guards on the other ſide, where I had placed thoſe of my own regiment, the towneſmen, and ſome voluntiers. Moſt of theſe ſouldiers were upon the guard every night, doing conſtant duty twelve nights together, and my ſelf was continually with them all that time, viſiting one guard or other, all the night.</p>
            <p>Friday, the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of July, Sir Thomas Fairfax drew neer the town, and that night and Saturday placed ſeverall guards within Musket ſhot of our works, and ſo continued without advancing further untill he ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the town, which was Munday morning the 21. of July, between one and two of the clock, at which time he brought on two bridges to paſſe his men over the Graffe, which were ſo narrow, that I believe not above two men could paſſe over abreſt, and one of theſe bridges ſailed in the bringing on, ſo that if theſe Pembroke-ſhire men had been ſtout and honeſt, it being their guard that he attempted to force, it is apparent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101713:4"/>how fruitleſſe his attempt muſt have proved. I was then in Eaſtover, and as I conceived, did heare ſome noyſe of the enemies preparation before they came on, and for the more certain diſcovery thereof, did ſend out twenty musketeers under the command of a Sergeant, being drawn out of Prince Ruperts regiment, who at their return, aſſured mee, that the enemy moved not, yet immediatly after that, the enemie came on, and marched with their bridge over Caſtlefield, where they had no ſhelter, from our ſhot, and if our men had not been falſe, they muſt needs have done great execution upon them; but theſe Pembrokeſhire men, although they fired very well, did little or no execution on the enemy; for they either ſhot over their heads when they ſhot bullets, or elſe ſhot nothing but powder, as they themſelves confeſſed after the town was ſurrendred, upbraiding divers Proteſtant Officers, calling them Papiſts, and asking them, whether they believed that they would fight againſt the Parliament to defend Papiſt Rogues?</p>
            <p>And yet I am aſſured, that there was not one Papiſt that was an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer within the Garriſon. At the ſame time that the enemy attempted Eaſtover, I hearing great vollies of ſhot from the other ſide of the Town, conceiving that the enemy might enter there, thinking this part ſecure, becauſe it was ſo well man'd, having left a reſerve of horſe and foot on that ſide of the water, to be ready on all occaſions to ſecond thoſe who guarded the line, and to prevent the enemies aſſaults, I rode with much haſte round the line on the other ſide of the town to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the towneſmen, and to obſerve if there were any danger of the enemies entring there; but before I could ride round the line, and return into Eaſtover again, the Pembrookſhire men had laid down their arms, and when I came back, were helping the enemy over the works, and above fourty of them entred. Major Michel, who commanded in chief over that Regiment, being ſhot, was carried off, and I found no Officer there, the reſerve of foot, and moſt of the horſe being gone, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I eſpied at a diſtance, five or ſixe horſe, which were moſt of them Officers, amongſt them were L. Col. Jones, and Cornet Welſh, whom I commanded to joyn with me, and to indeavour to beat out the enemy that was entred, which they did, and we forced back the enemy to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101713:5"/>top of the work, where wee could not charge them further, by reaſon of the ſteepneſſe of the bancks, where the enemy defended themſelves with pikes, and our own men mingled with the enemie, and fired upon us, and kill'd L. Col. Jones, being the next man unto me: I perceiving that it was impoſſible with horſe to beat the enemy from that ſtand they made on the top of the works, wheeled about my horſe, intending to ride to the other ſide of the line, to command from thence a party of Musketteers to force off the enemie; but when I came to croſſe the ſtreet, I found that by the help of theſe treacherous villains, the draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge was broken down, and the enemies horſe entred into Eaſtover, ſo that I found three were then ſo many of the enemies entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that part of the town, that it was impoſſible to beat them thence; whereupon I indeavoured in the beſt manner I could, to ſecure the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of as many ſouldiers as might be, out of Eaſtover, into the other part of the town, beyond the river; but my ſouldiers being in diſorder, and confuſion, the enemie coming on ſo faſt, hindred divers that were endeavouring to get over the river, and ſome were ſlain, amongſt which L. Col. Glanvile was one, who eſcaped from the enemie at the fight at Lamport, and came into the town, juſt as Sir Thomas Fairfax came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it. The enemie immediatly brought up their Cannon to force the drawbridge, which was the paſſage over the river, and by the ſhelter of the houſes, came within Piſtol-ſhot thereof, and before the chaines were faſtened, made ſome ſhot through him, and killed and wounded ſome men, yet we ſecured the bridge; and notwithſtanding all their Cannon-ſhot, which played continually upon us, we made two barro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadoes within the bridge, from whence I ſtird not, untill I ſaw thoſe works perfected. The enemy that night had raiſed three other batteries, the one in Caſtle-field, the other in the way going towards Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and the third, at the end of Weſt-ſtreet; theſe played moſt part of the day into the town, beſides a Morter-piece, which they ſhot often out of Eaſtover. After wee had finiſhed the works about the bridge, I having diſcovered where their Cannon lay, which battered us there, I cauſed the wreathed Gun to be brought down to that ſide of the town, and to be planted where I conceived it might moſt annoy the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101713:5"/>enemie and beat them off from their Cannon, there being a Blind made and no other ſecurity for their Gunners, which ſucceeded accordingly; for hereby we not onely beate them from that Gun, but alſo with this peece we battered Maſter Harvies houſe and drove the enemie thence, which was a great ſafety unto us. The enemie and we lay now onely ſeperated by the river, they having houſes and mudde walls on their ſide of the river, as uſefull for the ſafety of their ſouldiers, as our works, houſes, and mudde walls were unto us. Onely their walls had thatch of ſtrawe for their coverings, which we fired, and ſo made them too warme for them, to make uſe of them that day. The river was forda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at low water for horſe and foot to paſſe over. I know not what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion the enemie had, but that day about foure of the clocke in the afternoone, they ſeemed to quit Eaſtover in ſome diſorder, and drew off their Guns from their battery in Caſtle Feild, and fired that part of the Towne they were poſſeſt off, whereupon we ſallied, and ſeazed their Cannon wherewith they battered the drawe-bridge, and we tooke divers armes they had left behind them, and brought them into the Towne, but wanted conveniencie to draw off their Cannon, becauſe we had barrowcadoed the bridge. But within a ſhort time the enemie returned, and placed their guardes againe in Eaſtover. By this ſtorme we had loſt at leaſt ſix hundred ſouldiers, all the Welſh being turned to ſerve the enemie except about forty, which were in the inner Townemoſt of Sir Iohn Stawells Regiment, and the Briſtoll ſouldiers were taken priſoners, ſo that I had remaining about five hundred ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and townſ-men, that bore armes, the reſt being loſt in the ſtorme of Eaſtover, beſides we loſt two iron Guns, ſome ammunition and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion. Notwithſtanding this loſſe I ſo encouraged thoſe ſouldiers I had left, telling them that now the traytors were gone, we ſhould be the more ſecure, having none but ſuch as were faithfull remaining, and as we had fewer ſouldiers, ſo we had leſſe ground to defend. That night we wrought very hard to lyne our thinne workes, and to raiſe Blinds to prevent the enemie out of Eaſtover, who might elſe in divers places command the inſide of our Curtaines. The next morning being Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day about the ſame houre that the enemie ſtorm'd us, the day before,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101713:6"/>they attempted us again, but with no ſucceſſe, their ſouldiers not daring to aſſault our workes, but ſhouting very hard at diſtance, at length re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated without gaining any advantage, which was a great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my ſouldiers, being now confident, that the enemie durſt not attempt our workes, and that what they did the day before was by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with the Pembroke-ſhire men.</p>
            <p>That afternoone about two of the clocke Sir Thomas Fairefax ſent his third and laſt ſummons for the ſurrender of the Towne, to which I returned a poſitive refuſall. Immediately after a houſe was fired to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the weſt part of the Towne, and I going to give order for the quenching thereof, had not ſtaid long but newes was brought that the Towne was fired in divers other places, and ſome boyes apprehended who were actors therein, confeſſing that they had been hired to doe it by ſome of the Pembroke-ſhire ſouldiers. A Livetenant likewiſe was taken endeavouring as was pretended to fire the Church, conceiving the Magazine had beene there: The boyes confeſſion was a certaine proofe, but the evidence againſt the Livetenant was not ſo cleare. A houſe was likewiſe fired where the Gunners kept all their caſe and round ſhot, and ſuch other ammunition as was prepared for our Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and likewiſe moſt of our match was there conſumed, in ſhort the fire grew ſo great and terrible that the Towne ſeemed all of one flame. Thoſe houſes that were fired neere the lyne, made the place too hot and dangerous for any ſouldiers to abide there: the townſmen all ran off their guards to ſecure their goods and houſes, and drew off with them divers ſouldiers, by giving them money to aſſiſt them therein: So that the lynes were generally quitted, the Towne likely to be burnt all to aſhes, the enemie ready to aſſault us, and few or none could be gotten to make defence, moſt of our proviſion and ammunition burnt and deſtroyed by the fire: And the moſt part of the ſouldiers and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple crying out to make conditions; whereupon I call'd a Councell of warre, and by the advice of all or far the greater part of the Officers that were there preſent, I bekeve I may truely ſay by all of them that were then there, it was thought fit to ſend unto Sir Thomas Fairfax for conditions, which with much importunity I was perſwaded to doe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101713:6"/>after ſome of the cheife Officers and Souldiers of the Garriſon had by the appointment of the Councell of warre viewed the Towne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned anſwer that it was not poſſible to be held.</p>
            <p>All that were then preſent can bear me witneſſe, with what difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I was perſwaded to hearken unto conditions, and what induſtry I uſed to encourage the ſouldiers to defend it, but I have been ſince told by ſome of good credit, that there were others as ſolicitous to diſſwade them from it, being more ſtudious to preſerve their lives then their honours, telling the towneſmen and the ſouldiers, that there was no reaſon, now that they might have conditions, that they ſhould all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their lives, to ſatisfie the raſhneſſe of the Governour, who it may be, could not find means to reconcile himſelf to the Parliament; but for them, their offences were not ſo great, but that they might make ſatisfaction, which moſt of them have ſince done; and after their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto London, were quickly releaſed; by which perſwaſions, and other diſcouragements, eſpecially that of the fire, the whole town be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing probable to be burnt down to the ground, and moſt of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition and proviſion being already conſumed, there was a neceſſity of yeelding the town, and of accepting ſuch Articles as the Generall would give us, he having intelligence of our condition, and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it as well as our ſelves, both ſouldiers and inhabitants preſſing mee thereunto, diſſerting their guards, and applying themſelves wholly to exſtinguiſh the fire, which now ſeemed to overſpread the whole town. Whereupon it was agreed, that we ſhould draw up Articles ſuch as we intended to yeeld the town upon, and ſend them unto the Generall, which was accordingly done, and Mr. Ellyot ſent with them, who immediately returned, with other Articles, ſubſcribed by Sir Thomas Fairfax, which were ſuch as afterward we were enforced to ſurrender the town upon; by which, both officers and ſouldiers became priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to which I returned anſwer by Sir Jo. Hele, and Mr. Ellyot, that we would not accept thoſe conditions, and that unleſſe we might have our liberties, we were reſolved to abide the greateſt extremity, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101713:7"/>ſo gave order that the parley ſhould breake off. And I endeavoured in the mean time, to draw men to the works, for the defence of the town; but whileſt I was endevoring to draw men to the line, Mr. Ellyot returned with a poſitive deniall from the Generall, that he would give no other conditions; whereupon it was unanimouſly reſolved by all the Officers and Gentlemen preſent, that we ſhould accept thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions offered by Sir Thomas Fairfax. And I appeal unto all, who were at the meeting and tranſacting of the treaty, whether, when it was objected by ſuch Officers and Commiſſioners as were preſent, that I ſhould be held guilty of all the blood that ſhould be afterwards ſpilt, if I accepted not the conditions; and whether they did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what I would fight for, or what I would defend, for the town would be conſumed unto aſhes; and whether my anſwer were not, that I would fight for my liberty, or to have an honourable Sepulture in thoſe aſhes, but my perſwaſions could not prevail with them, for all unanimouſly preſt me to the yeelding up of the town; this is the truth, which I will juſtifie, concerning the delivering up of the town of Bridgewater, wherein I will appeale to all who were there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, whether I did ever abſent my ſelf out of apprehenſion of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or did not on all occaſions ſhew my ſelf ready to expreſſe my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and my loyalty with the hazard of my life.</p>
            <p>And whereas it hath been objected, that I ſold the town, I defie all the world, to proue that ever I held any correſpondence or intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with the enemie, or ever received any favour or friendſhip from the Parliament, or their Armie; nay, I have been ſo tender in ſeeking to the Parliament for any of thoſe things which they ordinarily afford to men in my condition, that I have forborn to ſue for them, fearing, that thoſe, who on no probable ground are ſo bold to ſcandall me, would eaſily be induced to miſconſtrue both our intentions, and interpret civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities diſguiſed corruptions. I confeſſe, after the ſurrender of the town, I was civilly treated by the Generall, and ſome of his Officers, and out of that civility, I am confident they will vindicate mee from all theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101713:7"/>aſperſions, if they be required thereunto. I loſt all I had in the town, which in goods and houſholdſtuffe, I am ſure was of a conſiderable value, not preſerving ſo much as mine, my wifes, or childrens clothes, which indeed were allowed us by the Generall, but after taken away by the Committee; and for ready money, the Generall allowed me to carry out thirty pounds, but truly I had not ten pounds when I left the town, but was enforced to borrow money to bring me to London, for I ſpent not only what I had allowed from his Majeſty, but mine own revenue was imployed in that ſervice, as thoſe who kept my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts can cleerely juſtifie, beſides what I borrowed and ingaged my ſelf, to ſatisfie for the publike ſervice.</p>
            <p>There was never any rationall man that was corrupt, but it was for ſome end or advantage, I am ſure I could have none in it, for I loſt all that I had in the world, not preſerving a peniworth of any goods; nor had I any conditions for my other eſtate, which hath been ever ſince in ſequeſtration. This juſtification I offer to the view of the world, and do challenge all my adverſaries to produce but a ſingle circumſtance to make their ſcandalls probable, which if they ſhall offer any, I ſhall not doubt, but by the teſtimony of perſons of honour, cleerly to convince their malice. All that I ſhall hereby deſire, is, that having in this adventure loſt all my eſtate, I may by the candor of thoſe that reade it, be preſerved in my reputation, and then, although few begreater ſufferers then my ſelf, yet none ſhall be more contented, becauſe in the whole progreſſe of this buſineſſe, I did nothing with relation to the truſt repoſed in me, that awakens my conſcience to repentance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
